hello everyone my name is greg and i def
staff welcome everyone to episode 17 of
the tactics game in unity
gameplay menu and rounds
while i will be explaining what we're
going to do in this episode i will clear
our root folder it gets a little too
crowded at this point
so in the last episode we have
implemented a turn system which grants
turn to player characters and allow them
to do player actions but right now after
executing all the commands we cannot
continue in any form so we want to
introduce a way to advance around in the
game so it will reset the ability of the
characters to do their actions
before we do that we want to introduce a
gameplay menu
through which you will be able to
control the game when you are in combat
create a panel called control panel
copy the command panel state into this
control panel so the shape and placement
of the panel will be copied
good
now let's add two buttons on this panel
and turn and close
so set close button to disable the panel
good
now i want to make it possible to open
this menu by pressing right mouse button
so select game manager let's minimize
all the components so it will be easier
to navigate our stack of components
create another new component called game
menu open this new script
here in the update if we press right
mouse button it will open the menu
and now if we launch the game i can open
the menu by pressing right mouse button
but there is a problem if i press right
mouse button when my character is
selected it will not deselect the
selected character and open the menu
overlapping with the command menu
we need to limit the ability to open
game menu if the command menu is opened
open game menu
we know that if our selected character
is inactive that means we are delivering
the commands to the selected character
or doing something else
so let's use it as a condition to be
able to open the panel
curse the reference and use its enabled
state as an exit gate
good i cannot open the menu if i have
selected character and delivering the
command to this character to be honest i
don't like this implementation we might
come back to this later in the series to
redo it
this episode is brought to you by
generous support of people on patreon
and members on youtube if you want to
join them link to my patreon in the
description and join button available
right now on youtube
ok we have a menu which you can open and
close now we want to make it possible to
advance the turn so our character can
act again
for this we will need to maintain list
of all active characters on this scene
select game manager and create another
new component called round manager
inside create a list for all characters
this character turn component on the
scene
then create a new public method called
admin which will add the character with
character turn component which we pass
as a parameter to this list of
characters initialize list if it's no
to be able to call this method easily
let's make the round manager to be
singleton
now in the character term
on start create and call a new method
called add to round manager
where we will call admi on the round
manager and pass this character tool
good
so we have a list of all characters
which can take turn in the round now
when we done doing taking our actions in
the round
we want to click on next round and it
will iterate around grants the ability
to act once again to every character
with character turn
so in the round manager create an
integer variable for round counter
create a new public method called next
round add plus 1 to the round counter
in this new method and iterate through
all characters
in the list and grant them a turn
this will set there can walk and can act
into true state so when the next round
is called all the characters will regain
ability to act in this round
now in the editor on the end turn button
call next round
there is a small confusion about turn
and round right now like we call button
and turn but we are calling next round
method don't worry this will be made
more clear in the next episode where we
will be separating characters into sites
or you know player and enemy iai side
hide the panel after you select end turn
good
now in the game we have an ability to
move character you cannot move two times
in the same round you need to call next
turn then you will be able to move
around again
good ok we have a problem right now
there is no way to back out of the
selected command if i select attack
that's it i'm stuck and you are executed
and if for example you are in the state
where you cannot attack anything which
means you cannot execute this command
like for example having an attack
command but there is no targets around
you you stuck without a way out
open command input
in it let's clean the right mouse button
input
and here we want to stop current command
add this to the attack command input 2
so we will be able to stop it too
to stop command input we need to call
deselect on the character enable the
ability to select character
and set is input to false
so to not repeat ourselves reuse this
part of the code
reuse stop command input in the attack
command 2.
good
okay it does allow us to reselect
character but it does not clear the move
and attack points if we cancel selection
to clear this we need to cache clear
utility
and in the attack clear attack
highlights
and in the move clear move highlights
and pathfinding
okay let's add a little more information
to the screen
let's add turn count and selected
position on the screen
create text objects for this
open round manager
create serialized field for this text
and create new method called update text
on screen where we will update the text
on the screen
by posting the round counter into this
text object
call this update on start and every next
round
reference the objects
and yes it works
now position open the mouse input create
a serialized field for position
in the update if we are outside the
selectable position on grid we will say
outside
and if we are selecting the node on the
grid put the position of that node into
the text
good
good this is it for this episode if you
have any questions or any ideas about
code please leave your comment below if
you're interested in seeing what will
come out of this please subscribe if you
want to support yourself you can find my
patreon in the description
special thank you to andrew v long the
soul has do dominic mckeowcha and fari
passer for their generous support with
best regards see in the next episode
you